[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is Samhita 42.8, translated as a horn blower.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, on one occasion, the Blessed One was staying near Nalanda in the Pavarika mango grove.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, Asibandha Kaputa, the headman, a disciple of the Nigantas, went to the Blessed One, and on arrival, having bowed down, he said to the Buddha,
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no, actually, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Blessed One said to him, Headman, how does Nīgānta Nāthaputta teach the dhamma to his disciples?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nīgānta Nāthaputta teaches the dhamma to his disciples in this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: All those who take life are destined for the state of deprivation, are destined for hell,
[SPEAKER_00]: All those who steal, all those who engage in sexual misconduct, all those who tell lies, are all destined for a state of deprivation, are destined for hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever one keeps doing frequently, by that one is led.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, the frequency of one's actions determines where one is being led to, in which rebirth, which hell, which consequences.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how Nigantha teaches the dhamma to his disciples.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then the Buddha said, well, if it's true that whatever one keeps doing frequently, by that one is led, then no one will be destined for a state of deprivation or destined to hell in line with those Nīgānta Nataputta's words.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you think, headman?
[SPEAKER_00]: If a man is one who takes life, then taking that into consideration, time spent taking into consideration, time spent doing and not doing of taking life,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the headman replies, well, yes, if a man is one who takes life, then taking into consideration time he spends doing it, whether by day or by night, then the time he spends taking life is less, which means he more frequently abides by not taking life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it goes on to repeat this about stealing, engaging in sexual misconduct, lying, basically about breaking the five precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, once the Buddha obviously showed him the flaw in that argument, he continues.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, there is the case, headman, where a certain teacher holds such doctrine, holds the view of all those who take life are destined for a state of deprivation, are destined for hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: All those who steal, all those who indulge in sexual misconduct, all those who tell lies, they're all destined for state of deprivation, destined for hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, kind of saying that, pretty much, if you would have engaged in any of these acts, you're done, you're going to hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if a disciple has a faith in that teacher, he would then have a thought occur to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: All those who take life are destined for a state of deprivation, are destined for hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are living beings that I've killed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter if it's accidental or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have actually killed some living beings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, I am destined for a state of deprivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am destined for hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: He then fastens on to that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if he doesn't abandon that conviction, he doesn't abandon that state of mind, does not relinquish that view, then he will be basically pretty much as if carried off, placed in hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, he's heading to hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it repeats again the same type of, let's say, fixed view for the other remaining precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha contrasts that with... there is a case, headman, where a Tathāgata appears in the world, worthy of and rightly self-awakened, with clear knowing and conduct, well gone, unknower of the world, unexcelled trainer of those to be tamed, teacher of human and divine beings, awakened, blessed.
[SPEAKER_00]: He, in various ways, criticizes and censures the taking of life and says, abstain from taking life.
[SPEAKER_00]: abstain from stealing, abstain from sexual misconduct, abstain from engaging in such sexual misconduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: He criticizes and censors telling of lies and says abstain from telling of lies.
[SPEAKER_00]: A disciple has faith in him.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Blessed One is in variety of way criticizes and censors the taking of life and says abstain from taking life.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are beings that I have killed to a greater or lesser extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in this life, or you could even stretch it and say, well, in the past, past lives, I must have done it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was not right.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was not good.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am remorseful because of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I cannot undo what I've done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, reflecting thus, he abandons right there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandons right then the taking of life and in the future refrains from taking of life.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is how there comes to be the abandoning of that evil deed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this point is important because it shows that how he abandons the past evil deeds that he can't change.
[SPEAKER_00]: He cannot undo what he'd done, but taking on remorse of that action
[SPEAKER_00]: He abandons taking of life and refrains from future taking of life.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're going to address that later on, specifically that question.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is that it is in the present, now, that you would abandon both past actions that you cannot fix anymore and future actions that you haven't performed yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it goes on saying, the Blessed One, in a variety of ways, criticizes sensual stealing, engaging sexual misconduct, telling of lies, and then repeats the same type of reflection, remorse, on account of the five precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is where I added a part from Agama, Sangita Agama 916, that adds, kind of, like a bit more description to the same, to the same, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Passage from Pali, which says, from former times, because of my ignorance and lack of wisdom, I had the intention to kill.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, now I feel remorse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although, I cannot make those evil deeds cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of this remorse, in the future, I shall be free from killing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And likewise, free from stealing, sexual misconduct, and lying.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it quite clearly points how, on account of that remorse, you already
[SPEAKER_00]: Figuratively speaking, create some space between you and the previous actions of the unwholesome kind that you would have done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by taking on that remorse correctly, that's how you already indicated in the future, well, you won't be going in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says, I will then also attain complete fulfillment of true release of mind and the true release of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once those releases are fulfilled, I will not slander the Noble Right View.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, when he fulfills those releases, there will be no point, no part of the
[SPEAKER_00]: The right understanding of what the practice is, that he can sort of misconceive and see an obstruction as a non-obstruction and so on, like those other examples in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by the condition of the right view, I will be born into good destiny and in the heavens and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, then the Pali Sutta just kind of sums up that having abandoned taking life, he refrains from taking life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having abandoned stealing, he refrains from stealing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having abandoned sexual misconduct, he refrains from sexual misconduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having abandoned lies, he refrains from lies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having abandoned divisive speech, he refrains from divisive speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having abandoned harsh speech, he refrains from harsh speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Idle chatter, he refrains from idle chatter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Covetousness, he becomes uncovetous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ill will,
[SPEAKER_00]: anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: He becomes one with the mind of no ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having abandoned wrong views, he becomes one who has right views.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all of these were pretty much the practical progressive developments of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Act by body, act by speech, and then act by mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The the final roots of covetousness, ill will, wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then Samyutta Agama here adds another kind of, as I said, aspect to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, village chief of headmen, these wise disciples of long-hearing practice like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: At all times, day and night, they observe whatever arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the mind's intention to kill arises, they reproach themselves, saying this is wrong, this doesn't fit.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the mind's intention to kill does not arise, they remain without resentment or hatred.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the mind develops friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, observing whatever arises, it's not like just metaphysically thinking about theoretical aspects of, oh, everything arises, and then, like, mere observation of stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it continues and tells you exactly what to look for.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the mental intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we're not even talking about the coarse acts anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would have been abandoned way beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, he trains further in looking at the mind's intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if intention to kill arises, even before he allows the proliferation of it, before he starts to carelessly feed it through the thoughts of anger and cruelty and harm and so on, he already recognizes that the intention of the level of that wild animal, on the level of that citta, and says, whoa, this is already wrong, this doesn't fit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he already puts brakes on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, if the citta does not have the intention to kill, then it remains without resentment or hatred.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind, that citta, develops friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he recognizes that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he's not going around telling himself everything arises, or going around reproaching his citta for everything and nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's for the clear intentions of harm, of unwholesome, of covetousness, of ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: He abandons those by recognizing even intentions towards those before they even fully manifest as the proliferated examples.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says then, the mind then develops friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, when there is not even an intention to kill or harm present in that citta, that animal is friendly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, I always give the simile of the dogs or animals.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know when your dog is incapable of biting
[SPEAKER_00]: A stranger, you know, it has... it doesn't have it in him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you trust it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this will be the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would have trained your own mind, your own wild animal, and now you trust it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know that it cannot even have the intention to harm, let alone actually act out of that harm.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, that mind is friendly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That... it's a state of friendliness regardless of who or what comes at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's people provoking it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind, the animal trained in friendliness, cannot become unfriendly, because you recognize the value of it, you insisted on that training rightly, and you would have developed it through abandoning the intentions of ill-will, the intention to kill, not through, as we're going to see later, random mechanical practices of visualizations and mantras and repeating phrases and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Āgama continues, says, having generated this joy on account of that friendliness, rapture arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: With rapture, the mind becomes tranquil.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the animal calms down even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: With that calmness, with that tranquility, it experiences pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: With pleasure, one becomes composed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: With composure, the noble disciple, with the mind of friendliness, without resentment, without jealousy, without ill will, becomes broad and limitless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Filling one quarter of space with right composure, the second, the third, up to the four quarters, he fills with the result of his composure on account of abandoning even intentions to harm, intentions to ill-will, intentions to kill.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, filling up the quarters is the... pretty much spreading the outcome, let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the outcome goes in all directions, because it's already unlimited.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does not mean he fabricates the limitless state of mind through traveling in all directions and then patching them together or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then the second, then the third, up to the fourth quarters.
[SPEAKER_00]: Throughout the entire world, in all directions, with a mind of friendliness, without resentment, without jealousy, without ill will, broad and limitless, well cultivated, pervading all directions, dwells in the right composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So Pali basically says, kind of repeats, having abandon taking of life, wrong livelihood, and then he just says that disciple of the noble ones, thus devoid of covetousness, devoid of ill will, unbewildered, alert, mindful, keeps pervading the first direction with the mind imbued with friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Likewise the second, likewise the third, likewise the fourth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is where people think, aha, okay, so this is what I do.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to practice metta, I keep pervading the directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then those same people overlook the very line
[SPEAKER_00]: Beforehand, that still confirms the very expanded passage that comes from Agama, which is, are you devoid of covetousness, completely devoid of intentions of ill-will, completely unconfused, alert, being unable to be unmindful?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, yes, pervade, you know, the directions of East and West and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this is just overlooked as, aha, yeah, sure,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, I'll move on to the method of pervasion and all these practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: While, in reality, this line is pretty much abandoning the five hindrances, like, thoroughly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandon possibilities towards the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just, oh, I'm temporarily not engaging in unwholesome actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, I'm free from the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that would basically put you in the very first wrong view that this sutta started with.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm temporarily not engaging, therefore I'm fulfilling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, most of the times you are temporarily not engaging with anything unwholesome, but you're still well within the domain of hindrances and you cannot claim that you're devoid, that your citta, your animal is devoid of covetousness, devoid of possibility of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if something comes that provokes it, it will very much react.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's nothing wrong with this Pali passage in a sense of... yeah, there it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says the disciple of the noble ones, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: somebody with the right view already, on account of purification of his own behavior, frees himself from hindrances and then that mind of friendliness spreads in all four directions, all-encompassing, abundant, expansive.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the result of his correct setup and withdrawal and abandonment of things one should abandon.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it's the simile.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as a strong trumpet blower can notify the four directions without any difficulty in the same way when the liberation through friendliness is thus developed, thus pursued, any deed done to a limited extent no longer remains there, no longer stays there.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll address that after we read to the sutta, like what that means specifically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, it goes for the other brahmavihāras.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are like the stock phrases, pointing out that there is a refinement to the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, friendliness, compassion, appreciation, equanimity, metta, karuṇa, mudita, upeka.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the end, Asibandha Kaputa, the headman, was obviously very impressed and he said, magnificent Lord, just as if he were to place upright what was overturned, to reveal what was hidden, to point out the way for the one who was lost, to carry a lamp into the dark, so those with eyes could see forms in the same way the blessed one, through many lines of reasoning, made the dhamma clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he went to the refuge and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that concludes the sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the points to consider, the questions that can be raised on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I already said, from that initial nirgānta's point of view, most people, most of the time, already keep eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I heard it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I heard people saying, like, oh, do you live by even five precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you live by precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, yeah, like, most of, basically, because most of the time, I'm not breaking them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I even heard monks say that as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in response to a question of how to deal with, like, thoughts of sensuality that come up throughout the day and bother one who is, like, restrained and living in the monastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the answers they were given were like, well, you know, most of the time you don't go around thinking about those things, so don't worry about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like... it's exactly Nigantha's... kind of falls into that Nigantha's view.
[SPEAKER_00]: That... well, from that point of view, most of the time, you don't do most of the unwholesome stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, what?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're already an arahant?
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no problem at all?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the question that's... that obviously naturally poses itself is what's the difference between someone who can rightly say that they keep the precepts and someone who isn't keeping them, they just circumstantially kind of uphold them until they break them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most of you already understood from the previous discussions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically, the difference is whether you took them on in a form of your intention, your decision, in a form of being taken on indefinitely, without an expiry date.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you break them, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even if you end up breaking the priesthood due to the weakness, if you still took them on in an indefinite sense,
[SPEAKER_00]: That can still result in actual progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't take them on, in that infinite or indefinite sense, even if you don't break them, you won't make any progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as the Āgamas parallel to this, that I included, points out, you need to basically...
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is on the level of your intention to do these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not even on the fact that you did it, or that you might still be doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to get to the root, to the layer of where that intention of mine to kill, to harm, to commit sexual misconduct and so on, you need to have withdrawn yourself physically from it, purify the speech, so that then these mental levels can become apparent and addressed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why that determination that would pertain into infinity, or I will train under the precepts, even five for that matter, can serve as some sort of beginning of the training.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, as I said, there's a big elephant in the room of still being immersed in sensuality and expecting your mind to grow.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, hypothetically speaking, taking on even one precept
[SPEAKER_00]: But in that ultimate sense, and we'll see why is that relevant, like, further down this discussion, even in that ultimate sense, taking even one precept brings you to the level of that intention to then break it or not, when circumstances, like, sort of create such conditions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not taking it in that ultimate sense, as I said, you could be keeping all of the monks' rules, if you want, and still actually not grow on account of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, like, even that intention to keep the precepts that you made beforehand, even after you break them, that intention can still remain and be picked up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that intention would be the direct reason, then, for feeling remorseful, for feeling regretful, responsible for your actions and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without it, everything becomes sort of negotiable, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, of course, central mind, we all know what directions will negotiations lean.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, eh... Yeah, so somebody asked, like, can one say that the reflections of a faithful disciple, mentioned further in the Sutta, are the equivalent to taking full responsibility for one's life and actions?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the level of, oh, but I cannot undo what I've done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that means one takes responsibility for the pain of those past actions without trying to manage them and with the danger of acting in the future in the same way revealed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's exactly... that exactly comes through that responsibility of taking it on and not just justifying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I did it because I didn't know or this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: I did it full stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter why.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter if I was coerced in doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I chose to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I acted out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on me.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing that can sort of diminish that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, obviously, like, that can lead, you know, people could think like, aha, okay, so I blame myself for everything, but that's going too far the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't... you don't... that guilt that comes on account of recognizing the stuff that you did, well, now you also need to harness that guilt, not just feed it sort of carelessly like a wildfire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the point is,
[SPEAKER_00]: There are things you did that you can't change.
[SPEAKER_00]: But from now onward, when you recognize that, every single thing you are responsible for means every single thing you could do rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that that's exactly the point and why the Buddha contrasted that type of reflection, because that whole view, like when he said that there is a... some teacher might believe that whoever kills or commits anything immoral goes to hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha said, well, his disciples would then recognize and say, well, I did that, therefore I go to hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if they don't change the view of that, they will go to hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's basically, it's like a form of determinism.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, they say, okay, so whoever kills, it's done.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's doomed.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is nothing he can do about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've killed, therefore I can't do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when they can actually do something about it, I here and now abandon the intention for future
[SPEAKER_00]: Actions of the same kind that bind them to the past ones as well, they remain bound to the past actions on account of their view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, they go to hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, like, how can a person use the remorse rightly, as I said, and make sure that the future actions of breaking the precepts are not done, abandoned?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, now you know that in the future you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you know now that you won't break the priesthood in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, obviously, that takes training.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just decide or figure out mentally or theoretically and then you know for sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know through training it right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is it that you train right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, for example, you contemplate the worst-case scenario.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you say, I will not kill.
[SPEAKER_00]: I might have killed.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't change that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But from now onwards, I will never kill indefinitely.
[SPEAKER_00]: I take on this precept.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Great.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, add to that scenario.
[SPEAKER_00]: How about if somebody comes and attacks me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or how about if somebody comes and attacks my children?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or my wife?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or things that are dear to me?
[SPEAKER_00]: How about if somebody comes and starts stealing things that I find important and necessary for my life?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's my answer there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would I then
[SPEAKER_00]: Kill, or harm, or act out of ill will, because I feel justified.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you see your mind moving towards... Well, you will already know the answer, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you start posing those questions in a serious manner, you will already know where your mind is leaning towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already know what it would want to do, what the animal will want to, kind of, perform.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you recognize, aha, okay, so that's not abandoned in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm keeping the precepts now, but it's obviously conditional.
[SPEAKER_00]: I would like it to be indefinite and unconditional commitment to those principles of behavior, but my mind rejects that idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I ignore it and pretend and turn a blind eye and hope that those scenarios will never come up in the future, therefore I will remain pure in my precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do I actually train the mind so that it literally, even if somebody comes in, starts attacking things that are dear to me, I will... my mind will be unable to wish it harm.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be unable to abandon the four pervaded directions of friendliness they would have developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is an actual contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like that Salekha Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: What the Buddha described, what the actual effacement is, what actually burns away the unwholesome asavas and kilesas, it's such reflections of others may be harm, here we won't be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others may cause harm, here we won't cause harm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others may be deceitful, here we won't be deceitful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others... and so it lists all these unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it means that everybody else
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, there will be no exception.
[SPEAKER_00]: That will not be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order for that to sink into that wild animal and become its own value, you need to train it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to keep bringing up these scenarios and see if the animal is wound up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, okay, leave it with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leave it with that wound-up state.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until it settles.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then bring it up again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then bring it up again and leave it until it settles.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eventually, keep bringing it until the animal doesn't even come up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has actually accepted and started seeing for itself that, oh, it is actually better.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even in the most extreme scenario, I will be untouched by suffering if I don't act.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I act, that's when the not just present suffering will hit me, but it will connect me to everything else in the past that I might have done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the thought of freedom from past and future through the reflection here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what we said.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the actual effacement.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the actual purification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, if somebody not established in the precepts, not established in the sense restraint, nowhere near the right view, starts contemplating the worst-case scenarios,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, even they, if they do it rightly, could have some benefits.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are all those, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know, like half a dozen of, like, renowned psychotherapy schools and stuff that use exactly these techniques of bringing up traumas and stuff to have your... to maintain the emotional non-response towards it until it becomes a norm.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, triggering sort of memories and so on, you bring up, so that you stop being triggered by it, through non-acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even contemporary householder, kind of psychotherapist, they have no intention of abandoning the whole sphere of dukkha, recognize the value in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, imagine you pair that practice with the actual precepts, taken indefinitely, with the actual sense restraint, taken indefinitely.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the effacement that leads to complete freedom from suffering no other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and that's how you will know what you... what you won't be able to do in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: I kept saying that to people.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, sometimes you imagine a scenario and you get... you... the pressure arises because you don't know what to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: What would be the right thing to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: And often people ask that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What should a Buddhist do if such and such thing happens?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like you're looking at it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about what to do and figure out what you should do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about being completely, 100% clear of things you will not do, regardless of the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, that, as I said, value, that recognition, has had to sink down to the citta as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you have confidence that you know you won't act, because the animal won't act.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how you can... you can know what you're becoming capable of.
[SPEAKER_00]: And doesn't matter what scenario people might throw at you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're incapable of doing certain things and that's where the freedom comes from.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would have severed any connection with those unwholesome intentions that you would have maintained presently through not practicing such reflections and clearing out that connection through the possibilities of I could still act in this or that way if I'm pushed or pressed or similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when your mind is presently not moved on account of any future prospect and scenario, you know, like maraṇasati, the contemplation of death, all of these things, it's exactly the same purpose.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the mind is completely not moved, not frightened, not doubtful, when the hindrances are basically abandoned,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you will know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I know that now I'm free.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows the mind is free.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows he's free and he knows that his mind is free.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows that he knows the freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's understood on both levels.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by introducing such scenario, you would be training your mind to stop resisting them, even on the level of such possibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, there's the question that's also raised.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, what is it meant by that part in the sutta which says, Thus pursued any deed done to a limited extent no longer remains there, no longer stays there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it means exactly this.
[SPEAKER_00]: When your citta is staying presently, in regard to future possibility, possibilities, all the past actions as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have no bearing on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like that, you know, the drop of dye in a sea.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will not be able to color the sea, because the amount of water is so expanded, in comparison to a drop of dye.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, if you put a drop of dye in a little teacup, it will be fully affected by that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the difference between that limitlessness of the mind that's developed through abandoning even intentions towards ill-will, intentions towards hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, even the most horrific act that you could have done in the past, will be a just drop of dye in the sea.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be completely, well, unperceivable, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will have no bearing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I guess, a few more examples of the right reflecting, as I said, the right contemplation of scenarios, investigating your own actions,
[SPEAKER_00]: Investigating future actions, investigating, as I said, possible scenarios that might make you or pressure you to act in those future ways, and then, like, drilling in the information to your own citta that, no, those acts will not be done even in such scenarios, and then the citta will be all tense and upset or anxious, and then you have to endure it, and it's like, that's the training.
[SPEAKER_00]: You present a perception to the animal,
[SPEAKER_00]: And you leave it there until the animal calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you take it beforehand, the message you convey is... to the animal is, aha, okay, so my resistance to these ideas and perceptions works, because I resisted, and he got afraid and removed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now he's not bringing it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I keep doing that, and that's how I won't have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how citta remains untamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, contemplating non-ownership, contemplating possibility of loss, all the contemplation in the suttas, the repulsiveness, all that, leads exactly to the same way of containing your mind within those beneficial, but highly unpleasant, perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, that's why, again, you can't stress this
[SPEAKER_00]: Often enough, you need to have kept the presets in order to form some sort of container.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you might end up like those monks, they were jumping off cliffs and stuff, because they couldn't bear it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, be careful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so yeah, the part about the meta.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sort of a difference
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the addition, let's put it that way, that's included in that āgama, that kind of describes it a lot more organically, that development of metta practice, as opposed to just these blocks of memorized kind of lines during the oral transmission, that kind of lost all the nuance in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: It points out, that āgama part points out, that one dwells day and night practicing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not a quick method.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not something you, like, just... up to this morning, you were unestablished in your behavior, in precepts, and then just decide to, okay, now I abandon it, and then within five minutes you enter... you abandon hindrances, because there's nothing bothering you at the moment, you enter jhāna, or practice metta, or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You practice day and night, because the liability
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibilities of acting in this way, there are layers of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, these intentions to harm, to engage in sex, to break the precepts, to all these things, those intentions
[SPEAKER_00]: They can be very refined and more and more refined the more you look at them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why you need to keep bringing up scenarios and so on to see if they still come up.
[SPEAKER_00]: To see if there is still leaning in that direction for the mind to act in those ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: If, say, you didn't eat enough, you didn't sleep enough, you were tired, somebody upset you, experienced some fear, some doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's like, you gotta be purifying that for who knows how long.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the training.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, again, in the suttas, you find the same, just it's usually condensed to, like, one line when he says, oh, he dwells diligently purifying his mind from our wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as I said, due to the whole contemporary views through which people read the suttas today, they tend to not not even consider those lines that are there, and only consider the lines that support the view of, okay, so I do the method, I do the technique, I do the practice, I do spreading of metta and visualization of love, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meta is the friendliness of an animal that's unable to hate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unable to hate, because you abandoned every slightest intention towards hate, regardless of why it would happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to practice brahma viharas, and both parallels, Pali and Agama agree, you have to abandon the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, next time you're thinking that your meta visualizations help you,
[SPEAKER_00]: Ask yourself, have you abandoned hindrances beforehand?
[SPEAKER_00]: If the answer is no, they are not metavisualizations.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... Yeah, so there's a few more questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, I already answered this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, the question is, like, is it correct to say that these successive phenomena, like joy, rapture, tranquility, pleasure, composure, don't occur in, say, an hour of right reflection or after some other practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly how it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as I said, if you, like, with the help of this āgama, you get that there are, like, oh, implications of, like, a long period of time of development.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you realize you could read Pali in that way as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, there is a line there that he says that he abandons.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's devoid of covetousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's free from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Devoid of the hindrances, it's like, that will take some time.
[SPEAKER_00]: That will take some understanding, wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's no, like, five-minute metta meditation, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no five-minute any meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is it case that these successive beneficial qualities are born on account of what's being abandoned, rather than tangible positive effort of developing these qualities, specifically, as I said, patching them up through these practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's, yeah, of course, it's, as I said, it's through, and as the Sutta says, it's through abandoning intention to kill.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, abandoning intention of ill will and harm, let alone the act,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through abandoning the intention to go in the direction of harm and killing, animal becomes friendly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not through cultivating intention of friendliness, animal overrides its liability to kill, which is how people today would like it to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's the difference between jhāna and developing metta?
[SPEAKER_00]: Given that both sort of come on the basis of abandoning the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, technically speaking, I would say, you develop jhāna
[SPEAKER_00]: Towards the, say, internal aspect of your point of view, and the development of brahma-vihāras is toward external aspect from your point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just two opposite directions of the same limitlessness that's... that the mind is developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, the... the difference is also, like, quite specifically, jhāna would be outlined by the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Withdrawal by the separation, segregation from the unwholesome states, chief of which sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Metta is outlined by the withdrawal from unwholesome states, chief of which this deal will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it kind of depends where your animal is leaning to more.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's often leaning towards sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not so much towards ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, yes, exactly, through developing and practicing and contemplating scenarios of a subha, presenting it to your animal until it learns to calm down and not react or not kind of resort back to sensuality, you're practicing jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your animal is prone to hatred, ill-will, irritation and so on,
[SPEAKER_00]: By contemplating scenarios that would prompt that up and taming your animal within them, you're training it to be friendly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, the result is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Limitlessness of the mind, which completely extinguishes you from any connection with what has done and what could be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, frees you from karma, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, it's also... one of you pointed out that Samyutta Agama says that it's the citta that develops friendliness, but the usual practices today is just you use your own thoughts, mano, images, repeating phrases, and trying, as I said, trying to fabricate stuff that would then magically just make your citta love everybody.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the last, I think it's the last, yes, the last question.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would successfully taking on the precepts unconditionally, as I said you must, for the sake of training, if you want to train,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you take the precepts in an unconditional manner, see the dangers and the perils of sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's sufficiently enough so that your own citta is turned away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you haven't, say, fully understood it and become anāgāmī or something, but you need to have had to abandon it equally, eh... unconditionally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like I will refrain from sensuality until I get the right view and then go back to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the entire training needs to be taken unconditionally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the eight precepts, or five precepts with celibacy, the speech as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why often the precepts, kind of from the eighth, they just change into these precepts that include speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all of the precepts are supposed to be training precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all of them are supposed to be training you in sotāpatti.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you take them on rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why in the suttas, when it says disciple established in virtue, it's synonymous with disciple being a sotāpanna, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what established in virtue means.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean I just happen to decide to keep the precepts and I don't reflect further or take them on indefinitely, but most of the time I don't break them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's nowhere near any useful basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the question goes further.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, I understand that some sensory strength is necessary just to keep the precepts, of course, but is it possible for Sotāpārthi to come before the official sensory strength step on the gradual training?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, definitely.
[SPEAKER_00]: You let the precepts of the aggregate of virtue, of knowing things you won't do, you let that sink deep enough into that animal for it to sort of come to realize, oh yeah, actually, this is better for me as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the sotāpārthi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then that animal can't turn against you, can't crave against things that are already understood as kind of inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inaccessible to ownership, inaccessible to craving, can't crave towards pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It recognizes where it comes from and it just cannot touch it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it was that inadvertent touching, of animal touching, of the pain that was causing the dukkha, not the pain itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like the two arrows, sutta, the first one and the second one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, should one ever move on to the next step of increased sensory strain before they know for sure that they have successfully taken on the precepts unconditionally?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's not going to be that black and white.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will probably be moving, sliding back, moving forward, sliding back, while working on cementing the unconditional determination behind the precepts, even if you fail and break them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You really try to drill in that it will never be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every single time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, even when it's done, that weight of remorse sets in and actually pushes the mind in the direction of growth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether the mind wants it or not, it will have to go that way.